Maris B. Pierce papers
Buffalo History Museum. Research Library
Maris B. Pierce papers
1787 - 1884
1833 - 1874
(1.0 linear ft.) 2 boxes
Pierce, M. B. (Maris Bryant), 1811-1874
The Buffalo History Museum 1 Museum Court Buffalo, NY 14216 Phone: 716-873-9644 ext. 306 Fax: 716-873-8754 Email: library@buffalohistory.org URI: http://www.buffalohistory.org
Collection is arranged into two rises:
I. Personal papers, 1834-1884
II. Seneca Indian papers, 1787-1874
Mary Jane Carroll; gift; 1884/10/04; unknown
Researchers wishing to access this collection must apply for a Scholar Pass and present valid photo ID upon arrival to the library.
Maris B. Pierce was an educated Seneca Indian who lived most of his life on the Buffalo Creek and Cattaraugus Reservations. An 1840 graduate of Dartmouth College, he was one of the first Indians to be receive a college education. He returned from college to the Buffalo Creek Reservation, where he was appointed an official interpreter and also taught in the Indian schools. Pierce served as recording secretary for Seneca delegations to Albany and Washington, D.C., where he was a highly successful and respected advocate for Seneca rights and Indian welfare.
Pierce, M. B. (Maris Bryant), 1811-1874; Indians of North America--New York (State); Quakers--Pennsylvania; Seneca Indians; Timber--New York (State); autograph albums; bills (legislative records); census records; speeches (documents); treaties; Clinton, George W. (George William), 1807-1885; Community of True Inspiration; Ogden Land Company; Seneca Nation of New York; Indians of North America--New York (State)
Correspondence with government officials, census officials, Indians, Quakers, friends and relatives, 1834-1874; sermons, speeches and other writings; copies of New York State and federal laws and bills concerning Indians, 1850-1874; and papers concerning the Seneca Nation, including Council minutes, 1833-1865, treaties and agreements, 1787-1844, financial reports, letters, and mss. written by whites about the Senecas, 1807-1874. Subjects include Indian emigration, timber sales, schools, self-government and relations with the Ebenezers, Quakers and the Ogden Land Company.
- I. Personal papers, 1834 - 1884
  - A. Pierce's life and papers, 1884
  - B. Correspondence, 1834 - 1874
  - C. Sermons, speeches and other writings, 1838 - 1868
  - D. Recommendations and authorizing papers, 1837 - 1868
  - E. Autograph album, 1852
- II. Seneca Indian papers, 1787 - 1874
  - A. Treaties and laws, 1787 - 1877
  - B. Correspondence, 1807 - 1874
  - C. Council minutes, resolutions, etc., 1833 - 1865
  - D. Other papers concerning government of the Seneca Indians, 1814 - 1873
  - E. Papers concerning emigration, religious activities, census and other matters, 1839 - 1871